Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series III: National Coordinating Committee, undated, 1930, 1937-1940, 1961, 1967; Box 3, and Oversized Folder.
  Box 3, folders 1-4 consist of correspondence from Razovsky and NCC staff written in response to requests or offers of help from Jewish social service agencies and individuals. Much of the correspondence concerns case files of German refugees trying to obtain affidavits and get on the quota system to secure visas. The item list below for Box 3, Folders 1-4 includes only significant letters and is not a complete item list. Among the correspondents is Louis Brandeis (Folder 1), Jack Brandon of the Joint Relief Committee in Havana, Cuba (Folders 1-4), Joseph P. Chamberlain (Folders 1, 2, and 3), Philip Cowen (Folder 4), Henry Morgenthau Jr. (Folder 3), Joseph S. Shubow (see Folder 3), Edward M. Warburg (Folder 4), A.M. Warren, Chief of the Visa Division for the U.S. State Department (see Folders 2, 3, and 4), and Stephen S. Wise (see Folders 1, 2, 3 and 6). The issues NCC managed included investigating sources of affidavits (see Folders 1 and 2), finding employment for refugee physicians and Rabbis (see Folders 1, 3 and 6), locating scholarships for German refugee students (see Folder 3), planning agricultural and farm settlements (see Folders 1 and 4) attempting to get visas for concentration camp internees (see Folders 2, 3 and 4), planning to relocate groups of elderly people (see Folder 3), and intending to set up an immigration relief system in Canada (see folders 2 and 3).
  The NCC was permitted to bring only 20 German refugee children per month into the United States (see Folders 3 and 4). Razovsky writes in a letter dated December 23, 1938 to Armand Wyle, of the Hebrew Orphan Home in Atlanta, GA; "... There is terrific pressure here in this office. We are getting thousands of inquiries about children…" (see Folder 4). A report abstract from the Movement for the Care of Children from Germany, British Inter-Aid Committee dated May 18, 1939 is located in Folder 6. Razovsky writes to Mrs. Andrew Fried, of the District Grand Lodge No. 2 on November 21, 1938 (eleven days after Kristallnacht); "... We have had at least 1300 callers each day this past week; a thousand letters a day come in; there are many hysterical people in the office - the atmosphere is tense and feverish..."(see Folder 2).
  The NCC explored quota limits and refugee situations all over the globe; frequent countries discussed include Cuba, Brazil, and Argentina. A report titled "General Survey of the Refugee Situation in Cuba" was issued by Jack Brandon of the Joint Relief Committee in Havana, Cuba on November 15, 1938 (see Folder 2). Razovsky writes to the Joint Distribution Committee on November 29, 1938 "... There is no doubt that Buenos Aires needs a strong person to go down and organize the community..." (see Folder 2). Ann S. Petluck writes to Razovsky on November 18, 1938 regarding immigration procedures in Nicaragua, Panama, Costa Rica, and Australia (see Folder 2).
  Folder 5 is dedicated to information on emigration to the West Indies, Central and South America and consists of correspondence, articles, and reports. Articles consist of "An Ounce of Prevention" written by Razovsky on how to prevent anti-Semitism in Latin America and "Brazilian Business" concerning immigrants helping Brazil's economy. Reports are numerous, the most voluminous are titled "The Present Status of Jewish Settlement and Jewish Migration to Brazil and the Argentine," by Razovsky in 1937; and "Summary of Information Received by the New York Agencies on Local Refugee Conditions in The West Indies, Central and South America, " unidentified author, dated May 1, 1939. Additional material on Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Mexico, Panama, and Peru is located in Folder 6.
  Folder 6 also contains correspondence and reports from various refugee relief projects. Among the items of interest include a statistical statement of NCC activities throughout the U.S. in July 1938. Emigration information is available for England, Greece, Philippines, and Switzerland. The Jewish situation in Italy is reported on by the American Joint Distribution Committee and sent to Razovsky on December 2, 1938 (see also Folder 3). An "Eye Witness Report of Rescue Activities of J.D.C. at Polish-German Border" is dated November 18, 1938. Razovsky compiled various case studies and correspondence from refugees, the latest date mentioned is November 30, 1938.
  Folders 7 and 8 focus on the tragedy of S.S. St. Louis, a steamer carrying 930 Jewish refugees that was turned away from Cuba and forced to return to Europe to reface the horrors of the Holocaust. Folder 7 contains undated, 1939, and 1967 news clippings and articles in German, Spanish, and English; 1939 correspondence from Joseph Chamberlain and Razovsky updating the refugees' situation; a letter in 1961 from reporter S.L. Schneiderman thanking Razovsky for her reminiscences; and several manuscript versions, including an undated news clipping, of Razovsky's retrospection of her experiences. Folder 8 consists of Spanish news clippings, dated June 1939, from various newspapers. Additional information concerning the SS St. Louis is available in Folder 4 (see list of passengers, dated June 2, 1939; and correspondence dated June 5 and 6, 1939 ) and Folder 6 (see letter from Joseph Chamberlain dated June 15, 1939 ).
  See also: Series IV: National Refugee Service; Series V: AJDC/UNRRA; and Series VIII: United HIAS Service for immigration to South America.
  - Correspondence re: National Coordinating Committee - Aid for German Refugees, November 1-November 9, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence concerns case studies and obtaining affidavits. Additional documents of significance are noted below.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Hannah Hirshberg, Jewish Social Service Federation, San Antonio, TX., November 3, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "... there will probably be only two States in the Union who will allow physicians to take their examinations to practice before they become citizens of this country..."
    - Copy of air mail letter from Razovsky to Mrs. Isaac Swett, Oregon Émigré Committee, Portland, OR., November 3, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Urges Mrs. Swett to not "work hastily" in giving out affidavits before she received reports on the people from agencies abroad.
    - Copy of memo and letter from Razovsky to Florina Lasker and Pauline Salsberg., November 3, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Razovsky is responding to a complaint of inefficiency against HIAS.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Stephen S. Wise. Case study, Thomas Sherman., November 4, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Resettlement Division., November 4, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      A man from Wappinger Falls, N.Y. would like to resettle refugees on his farm.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Louis Greenspan., November 4, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "Rabbi Wise suggests you follow American Consul's advice."
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Professor Chamberlain., November 7, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Writes about the Oregon Émigré Committee, who has sent affidavits to people without an prior investigation and are trying to pass legislation that foreign doctors will be able to practice under special license.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Stephen S. Wise. Regarding case study, Thomas Sherman., November 8, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Rala Glaser, NCJW., November 8, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Regarding case study Leo and Liese Weiss. Cuba is closed, and may require a bond of $2000 per person for those coming directly from Europe.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Sol Hyman, Executive Secretary, Medical Refugee Control, Committee of the Western States, San Francisco, CA., November 9, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Discusses a plan for foreign physicians to settle in small towns that need medical care, however; the towns often cannot fund them.
  - Correspondence re: National Coordinating Committee - Aid for German Refugees, November 10-November 30, 1938; Correspondence concerns case studies and obtaining affidavits. Additional documents of significance are noted below. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Mr. Feinberg and Mr. Grunsbaum., November 10, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      The National Youth Administration urges their cooperation. She mentions a work project for girls.
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Employment Division., November 10, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding case study, Leopold Stoehr, who was sent to her by Stephen Wise.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Eva Shevell, NCJW., November 14, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding obtaining affidavits from Berlin. Russia quote is closed; preference quotas for almost all the countries are still open. Those who have been sent for must wait a minimum of twenty months on the German quota. She should not send anyone to Cuba.
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Sunny Schaefer., November 14, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Razovsky asks Schaefer to investigate a man selling affidavits.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mrs. E. L. Frankel, President of Toronto Section, League of Nations Society., undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding the possibility of Canada taking refugees in the near future, planning to set up a Canadian immigrant relief system.
    - Copy of a report "General Survey of the Refugee Situation in Cuba," issued by the Joint Relief Committee., November 15, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Dr. Kohs., November 15, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding Agudos Isroel Immigration Department, a branch of the European organization that deals with problems affecting Orthodox Jews.
    - Copy of memo by Razovsky to all Cooperating Committees., November 15, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      She is investigating the Immigrants Guidance Service, operated by Gaston A. Liebert, who is writing to synagogues all over the country for notification of job opportunities.
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Dr. Kohs., November 16, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding the Immigrants Guidance Service. She also describes the method NCC uses to investigate businesses.
    - Copy of memo from Ann S. Petluck to Razovsky., November 18, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Information from Consulates in Nicaragua, Panama, Costa Rica, and Australia concerning immigration procedures. Copy of memo from Razovsky to Dr. Kohs. Regarding the Immigrants Guidance Service. She also describes the method NCC uses to investigate businesses.
    - Copy of memo from Ann S. Petluck to Mrs. Hyam volunteer to Mrs. Schwartz., November 21, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Requests Mrs. Hyam to visit the Nicaraguan Consul and discuss the requirements for immigration to Nicaragua.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Greta H. Schaffner, Erie, PA., November 21, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Razovsky writes concerning German Jews "... There is nothing we can do to help these thousands of trapped unfortunates. They have no preference in the quota and their turns will come two years hence possibly..."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mrs. Andrew Fried, District Grand Lodge No. 2, B'nai B'rith., November 21, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Razovsky describes the "tense and feverish" atmosphere in her office; they have received 1300 callers each day in the past week.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Rabbi Stephen Wise., November 22, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding Mr. Epstein, a retiree, who tries to provide affidavits with no charge.
    - 15) Copy of letter from Razovsky to Charles Strull, Louisville, KY (fifteen days after Kristallnacht)., November 25, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Razovsky describes the last ten days at her office as "simply overwhelming." She recommends certain procedures for contacting individuals arrested in Germany.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Ruby Josephson, Paterson, N.J., November 29, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Regarding obtaining affidavits for people in concentration camps.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Samuel A. Goldsmith, The Jewish Charities, Chicago, IL., November 29, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Razovsky refers to the Refugee Economic Corporation in Ecuador as "an old dream."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Joint Distribution Committee., November 29, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      She urges a "strong person" to go down and organize the Buenos Aires community, to help the 1000 illegal immigrants become legalized. See also the following letter to Mr. Adolf Hirsch, Hilfaverein Deutschsprechender Juden, Buenos Aires, Brazil.
  - Correspondence re: National Coordinating Committee - Aid for German Refugees, December 1-14, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Walter H. Bieringer, Canton, MA., December 2, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Razovsky writes about the small quota in Poland, "... I think you are perfectly correct in saying that while economically they are much worse off than the German Jews, nevertheless, they are not being put in concentration camps in numbers and are not being tortured physically..."
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Professor Chamberlain and others., December 4, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding Cuba, the NCC will now be the only officially recognized agency.
    - Copy of open letter by the NCC., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Describes the procedure for sponsorship of prospective immigrants.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Frederick H. Crane, Mount Holyoke College, South Hadley, MA., December 6, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Razovsky writes that there are many families in Northampton who are willing to take German-Jewish children as guests; however the NCC has permission to bring only 20 children each month into the United States. Admission of large numbers of children needs to pass Congress legislation.
    - 5) Copy of letter from Razovsky to Rabbi Joseph S. Shubow, American Jewish Congress., December 6, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Shubow had telegrammed Stephen Wise, who referred him to Razovsky, concerning answering cabled requests through Hicem rather than through a Paris bank. She also refers him to the Coordinating Committee in Boston and HIAS of Boston. See following letter to Stephen Wise, enclosing telegram and copy of letter to Shubow.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to I. Edwin Goldwasser., December 6, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Concerning a plan to admit a group of elderly people into the country.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to J. Brandon, Joint Relief Committee, Havana, Cuba., December 6, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding giving dollar a day relief for refugees. She points out "that the Jews of Germany are not the responsibility of the United States alone-Jews all over the world must do their share and are equally responsible."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Benjamin Robinson, Canadian Jewish Congress, Montreal, Canada., December 7, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding the organization of a coordinating committee in Canada.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Robert Spivack, International Student Service., November 22, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Enclosing a copy of letter from R. Douglas Gleason, Chairman, Refugee Scholarship Committee, University of Wichita, Kansas to Professor J.P. Chamberlain, Columbia University, New York. University of Wichita has created a scholarship for a German refugee student, funded by non-Jewish students and townspeople.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mrs. Stephen S. Wise, Free Synagogue Child Adoption Committee., December 8, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      There will not be any children available for adoption in the near future due to the crowded quota.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Karen Featherman, President of Elmira Section of NCJW, Elmira, New York., December 12, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Razovsky says the NCC can only send for twenty children a month; they have 398 children in the U.S. that have been placed in homes in 85 cities.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Dan S. Rosenberg, Refugee Resettlement Committee, Philadelphia, PA., December 12, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding finding employment for rabbis overseas.
    - Copy of excerpt of immigration law sent to Dr. Farmer., December 13, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Defining the term "non-quota immigrant."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Bernard S. Gradwohl, Lincoln, NE., December 13, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      She writes it is impossible to secure visitor visas for persons now in concentration camps, the German government only releases those that can show they are emigrating permanently.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Rabbi Samuel Sandmel, The Temple, Atlanta, GA., December 14, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding two elderly people living in Rhodes. The U.S. government is negotiating with Italy to try and minimize their regulations against Jews. "It seems too dreadful to move these people in their eighties to some other country." Apologizes for her delay in response, her office is overwhelmed with work, particularly since November 10th and 11th.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Fred Kowalski, Brownsville, TX., December 14, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Regarding a hospital in Nuevo Laredo, Mexico that may have an opportunity for two or three doctors.
  - Correspondence re: National Coordinating Committee - Aid for German Refugees, December 15-28, 1938, January-June 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Edward H. Littman, Humble Oil and Refining Co., Legal Department, Houston, TX., December 20, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Responding to Littman's letter in which he states that he has furnished many affidavits and now believes the possibility of providing more is exhausted. He writes "further immigration into this country would be detrimental."
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to M.A. Solkin, Jewish Immigrant Aid Society, Montreal, Canada., December 20, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      The U.S. had ordered the withdrawal of all quotas abroad so they could be redistributed on a more equalized basis.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mrs. R. Bram, Dickinson, North Dakota., December 21, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Mrs. Bram had written that she wished to adopt a child; Razovsky writes that at present, there are homes already promised for the children coming in the next year.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Anita Henkes Weltner, Canal Zone, Panama., December 21, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky follows up on a request for a survey of immigration conditions in Panama. She also responds to Weltner's questions concerning loans to refugees, and describes the Refugee Economic Corporation.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Carter Alexander, Teachers College, New York., December 22, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Responding to Alexander's letter that he wrote to the German-Jewish Children's Aid, concerning sending two hundred children to a farm in Texas.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Sichel, Johannesburg, South Africa., December 22, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "... persons waiting in Mexico for their turn in the quota must wait just as long as if they were in Germany..." This is due to the redistribution of quota visas by the State Department.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Rabbi Samuel R. Shillman, Coordinating Refugee Committee, Sumpter, South Carolina., December 22, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky mentions which occupations can immigrate on a non-quota basis.
    - Copy of memo from Razovsky to Mr. Borchardt., December 23, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      She lists the reports she would like from him after he returns from his visit to Europe.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Armand Wyle, Hebrew Orphan Home, Atlanta, GA., December 23, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky describes the emotional exhaustion her office is going through, in responding to inquiries about children who cannot come yet due to the quotas.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Walter Rothschild, Abraham and Strauss, Brooklyn, N.Y., January 25, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky discusses the immigration needs in Trinidad.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Florina Lasker, NCJW., January 31, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky defines the procedure for helping people in concentration camps.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to A.M. Warren, Chief, Visa Division, Department of State, Washington, D.C., February 27, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky mentions the forced migration of Jews due to the demand of German police that Jewish organizations submit names of one hundred prospective emigrants daily.
    - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Mrs. A. Herzog, Galveston, TX., April 21, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Razovsky describes the possibilities of emigration for Herzog's family in Vienna. She mentions Shanghai ("starvation awaits those who go there"), Panama, and England.
    - Copy of list of passengers aboard SS. St. Louis., June 2, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Copy of open letter from Thelma K. Brown on NCC stationary., June 5, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Regarding the SS. St. Louis. See also following letters dated June 5th and June 6th.
  - Refugee Relief Work - Refugees to South America, undated, 1930, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Information on Colombia., 1930; 1 page. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "An Ounce of Prevention," by Razovsky., April 20, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      On preventing anti-Semitism in Latin America.
    - "The Present Status of Jewish Settlement and Jewish Migration to Brazil and the Argentine," by Razovsky., 1937; 70 pages. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Based on a trip she and Davidson took to Brazil and Argentina. Includes information on conditions in Brazil, conditions in Argentina, anti-Jewish sentiment affecting the Jewish immigration and local situations in the two countries.
    - Letter from Razovsky, Executive Director of NCC, to Paul Baerwald., April 5, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      She's working with non-Jewish groups to get people to South America.
    - Letter from Ludwig Lorch to Razovsky (in Säo Paolo)., August 18, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      About some material that he's sending her.
    - Article from "Brazilian Business," 17:8., August 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      About the possibility of letting in immigrants who will aid Brazil's economy and industrialization.
    - "Digest of Reports and Letters from South America from Frances Eddy," National Federation of Settlements, N.Y.C., May 25, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Authorizing the Permanency of Stay of Foreigners"., July 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      From the Official Gazette of the Ministry of Justice and Interior of Brazil.
    - Letter to the Joint, N.Y.C., from the Joint, Paris., August 23, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Attached is a report concerning conditions for Jewish emigration to Mexico.
    - Confidential report from NCC about the conditions for emigration to Brazil, October 31, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Written by a congregation in Brazil.
    - Letter from Luiza Klabin Lorch, São Paulo Brazil, to Razovsky., December 9, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      She now has the immigration law in English.
    - Letter from George Warren, President's Advisory Committee on Political Refugees, to Razovsky and Joseph Chamberlain., January 30, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      About emigrating to Bolivia. Attached are letters, cables, and meeting minutes.
    - Report of Mr. David M. Bressler on Panama., February 11, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Memo from Mrs. Maurice L. Goldman, NCJW to Razovsky., February 13, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 5)